hi and welcome to the channel in this tutorial
we're going to continue our journey of learning
the GrandMA 3 lighting console one of the great
things about the GrandMA 3 consoles from ma
lighting is that everything is customizable that
can be really helpful because you can make the
user interface just the way you like it but it
can also be one of the things that make it really
hard to get started with ema lighting consoles in
both GrandMA 1 and GrandMA 2 you had to build
all your views from scratch when
you started out for the first time
GrandMA 3 gives you a little help with some
predefined views but you still have to know
how to change things around to be able to
have exactly the work environment you need
knowing what you need can be one of the hardest
things to figure out if you have very little
experience with lighting consoles and that's
why i'll try to explain this to you very slowly
let me know in the comment section if you
have worked with lighting consoles before or
even if this is the first time with a lighting
console i'm also interested in hearing from you
if you have any questions about the video and
if you need me to clarify something remember
to give the video a like if you find it useful
and maybe even click the subscribe button if you
don't want to miss any future episodes the reason
that i take it so slowly in these videos is that
i think it's important not only to know how you
do different things on the GrandMA 3 console but
i also think it's it's very important to know
why you do it when you're working with views
you need to know what's possible in the windows
and you need to know how to build your own views
this will help you later when you
figure out you need a different view
that the ones may build for you and it'll also
make you less afraid of breaking something
because it's quite easy to fix in the last
episode we looked at patching four different
lighting fixtures into the console we patched 48
fixtures and that was two types of moving lights
one type of strobe and some dimmer channels
if you missed that episode there's a link
in the top right corner right now maybe you want
to watch that first to to catch up to what we're
doing now to start out with views you also
need to know something about the way you can
call them you can build many different views
and you're not limited to a certain number
the way you set up your console determines how
much view real estate you want to make use of
let's start with looking at what ma lighting
built for you if you look here in the right side
of your window you can see some different
boxes with numbers on it you have fixture,
preset, sequence sheet, phaser, 3d, and help all these
are called views and you can click on each of them
and you can see the screen changes to a new
view if you open one of the other windows on
the console screen 2 or screen 3 you will notice
that you can select the same views on all screens
but you probably don't want to have the same
views on all screens so we need to get rid of
some of them to make room for some custom ones
we built ourselves so let's delete the entire
row of views right now go to the command
section right here locate the delete button
and click it close the command section on the
small x up in the top right corner notice that
the command line has the command delete ready for
you click the first view and it disappears we now
have deleted the first view from screen number
one but you still have it on all the other screens
actually you can still find it in the console's
view pool but let's look at that later do the
same for all other views delete all of them right
now to start over with a blank screen you navigate
to the small cog icon up here notice that there is
a small window over here called display here you
have the option of clearing your screen to start
over with a blank screen press delete this screen
now we are looking at a blank screen with
nothing on it and all the predefined views
has been deleted it's now time to start building
our own views the way we like it the screen on the
GrandMA 3 console is black but if you click on
it you'll be prompted by this box when you click
the screen you are prompted with a lot of options
so let's start with locating the group view you
find the group view under the tab pools when you
locate the groups icon click it with your mouse or
your finger if you are on a real GrandMA 3 console
this fills up the entire screen with small squares
every square is a place where you can store a
group a group consists of a selection of fixtures
selected in a certain order why that matters is
for a later tutorial just know that it's important
the group view has over a hundred potential
groups in it and we don't need that many
click and hold the small triangle in the
corner to scale the window to a smaller size
i think this is space enough for our small
demo show the group window is ready now we
need to populate the rest of the screen click
on the empty space and locate the presets tab
if you haven't patched any fixtures
yet the presets tab will be empty
if you want to learn how to patch see
the previous video on this channel
in the presets tab select position scale it
to fit the screen to the size that suits you
i think this is going to be enough click on
an empty cell again and find the color preset
scale it the way you want it do the same for gobo
do the same for beam and do the same for focus
if you made a mistake i need to close a window
click on the small ma logo in the top left corner
of the selected preset and press the delete
window the last thing we'll add in this view is
the 3d view it might be a little advanced for this
tutorial but i think it's very important that you
can see what you're doing and how it affects your
lighting fixtures in the next episode we will set
up our fixtures in the 3d view but let's just
save it into our view for now now we have made
our first view but we haven't saved it anywhere
yet let's do that navigate to the command section
press store notice that the command line
reads store close the command section and
click on the first view hotkey, congratulations
you have now built and saved your first view
labeling the view is important right now it's
no problem to remember what we have built but
later when your show grows it's important that
you can identify it again now we need to start
working with fixtures in our show remember in the
last episode where we patched our first fixtures
let's start with making some groups for the four
different fixture types remember what we call them
701 through 712 is mac viper profile
601 through 612 is mac aura xp
301 through 306 is atomic strobes and 101
through 1 12 is our generic dimmer channels
let's start from the top open the command
section and type 701 through 712 and press please
this will select all your Martin Mac Viper
profile spots click on the store button and
close the command section again notice that
store is written in the command line down here
click on the first square in your groups
window you have now made your first group to be
able to remember what you have stored where it's
very important that you always label or name your
groups luckily it's very easy click on the group
to make sure it's highlighted simply type all
vipers on your keyboard or directly on your screen
depending on if you are on a real console go back
to the command section and locate the clear button
click the clear button three times i'll come
back to later why you click it three times just
remember that you you have to click it three times
do the same for the other fixtures type
601 through 612 in the command section
plus the please button press store close the
command section and click the second square
you have now saved that group and there now
you can label it all auras clear three times
type 301 through 306 and stored on the number
three and call it all atomics and last but not
least type 101 through 112 and store in number
four and name it all dimmer we have now made four
groups in our new view there are many different
views and you have a lot of options in the Grand
MA 3 console when creating views but in this
tutorial we try to keep it very simple so if
you are a new user you have the option to follow
along and learn as you go in the next video we
set up four different fixture types in our new 3d
window it's quite simple to do that and when it's
done you can see exactly what you're doing when
we are starting to make some simple programming
if you find any value in these videos please like
the video and maybe even subscribe to the channel
so you don't miss any episodes in the future and
please let me hear from you in the comment section
if there's something you want me to clarify
you are also more than welcome to suggest
future topics we should cover in the video as
well thanks for watching and see you next time